Finding Aid for Frank Fitt Papers 1918-1973
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Frank Fitt Papers 1918-1973
Fitt, Frank, 1889-1982.
Clergyman, minister of the Grosse Pointe Memorial Presbyterian Church. Scattered correspondence, reminiscences of Henry Ford, sermons and other addresses concerning in part the issues of the day, notably international and domestic affairs, the depression, World War II, and relations with Russia.
85160 Aa 2
7 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Amy McCarthy, granddaughter of Frank Fitt (donor no. 6960 )
The collection is open for research.
The Reverend Frank Fitt was born September 10, 1889 in Limerick, Ireland. He received an A.B. degree from Williams College in 1911, and a B.D. from Union Theological Seminary in 1914. He went on to take his A.M. degree from Columbia in 1915, and his D.D. from Alma College in 1931. In 1918 he married Harriet Bradley, and they had two children.
From 1917-1930 Reverend Fitt was the minister of the Presbyterian Church of Highland Park, Illinois. Not only the leader in church affairs, he also participated in community organizations such as the Boy Scouts, the public library, and Lake Forest College.
In 1931 Reverend Fitt began his 27 year tenure as minister of the Grosse Pointe Memorial Presbyterian Church in Grosse Pointe, Michigan. Church membership grew from 675 in 1931 to 3000 in 1958, and under his guidance, two other Presbyterian churches were sponsored: the Grosse Pointe Woods Presbyterian Church and the First Presbyterian Church of Saint Clair Shores.
In 1958 Reverend Fitt and his wife retired to Ann Arbor where he continued his participation in religious and community affairs. He preached sermons at churches throughout the area and was a guest speaker at various club and organization gatherings. In addition, he worked with the Ann Arbor Senior Citizens Guild, The Friends of the Library, and the Dunworkin Club, and was Secretary of the Thursday Noon Luncheon Club. Reverend Fitt died in Ann Arbor on July 10, 1982.
The Frank Fitt papers are arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material. Of most interest to the historian should be Reverend Fitt's Sermons, Addresses, Reviews, and Memorials. Comprising the majority of the collection, they are arranged in two ways, by topic and by date. Particularly in his sermons, Fitt spoke often to the issues of the day. The researcher will find many interesting references to domestic and international affairs, including the depression, World War III and relations with Russia. Of further interest should be Mr. Fitt's reminiscences of Henry Ford, a friend of his for many years.
Subjects:
Clergy--Michigan--Grosse Pointe Farms.; Depressions--1929--Michigan.; Fitt, Frank, 1889-1982.; Ford, Henry, 1863-1947.; Grosse Pointe Farms (Mich.); Grosse Pointe Memorial Church (Grosse Pointe Farms, Mich.); Presbyterian Church--Michigan--Grosse Pointe Farms.; United States--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Dwellings--Michigan--Willow Run.; Erosion--Michigan.; Playgrounds--Michigan--Willow Run.; Political elections--1948.; Willow Run (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Willow Run (Mich.)--Playgrounds.
Contributors:
McCarthy, Mary Fitt.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Sermons.
- Alphabetical File
  - Biographical (Box 1)
  - Articles (Box 1)
  - Beatitudes Manuscript: The Message of The Beatitudes (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Beatitudes Manuscript August-September, 1922 (Box 1)
      (mostly letters from publishers giving permission to quote material)
    - Leaving Highland Park, Illinois, Presbyterian Church
      incoming correspondence
      - December 1930 undated (Box 1)
      - January 1931 (Box 1)
    - Leaving Grosse Pointe, Michigan, Memorial Church 1958
      - Undated (Box 1)
      - July-August 1958 (Box 1)
      - September-December 1958 (Box 1)
    - Vacation: European 1956 (Box 1)
      (collection of Fitt's letters re: his trip abroad with his wife)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
      (includes typewritten copy of 1812 letter from German youth entering the German army)
  - Dunworkin Club (includes papers presented) (Box 1)
  - Ford, Henry: Reminiscences Of (Box 1)
  - Presbyterian Church, Highland Park, Illinois (Box 1)
  - Relationship Between The Fitts And The First Presbyterian Church Of Ann Arbor, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Sermons, Addresses, Reviews, Memorials
    (by topic)
    - Anniversary, Church (Box 1)
    - Anniversary, wedding (Box 1)
    - Apostles' Creed (Box 1)
    - Armistice Day (Box 1)
    - Bible, The (Box 1)
    - Book Reviews (Box 1)
    - Bunyan, John (Box 1)
    - Carpenter, Charles William (Box 1)
    - Charges (Box 1)
    - Children's Stories (Box 1)
    - Christ (Box 1)
    - Christ In Art (Box 1)
    - Christmas (Box 1)
    - Church, The (Box 1)
    - Church Extension (Box 1)
    - Church School (Box 1)
    - Commencement Addresses (Box 1)
    - Communion Addresses (Box 1)
    - Courage (Box 1)
      folder 1
    - Courage (Box 2)
      folder 2
    - Cross, The (Box 2)
    - Dale, Robert W., of Birmingham (Box 2)
    - Easter (Box 2)
    - Faith (Box 2)
    - Father and Son (Box 2)
    - Foreign Missions (Box 2)
    - Friends of Jesus (Box 2)
    - God (Box 2)
    - Handicaps (clipping) (Box 2)
    - Holy Spirit (Box 2)
    - Installations (Box 2)
    - Kingdom of God (Box 2)
    - Lent (Box 2)
    - McPherson, Aimee Semple, In Chicago (Box 2)
    - Men's Work (Box 2)
    - Memorial Addresses, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Memorial Day (Box 2)
    - Miracles (Box 2)
    - Morse, Charles Frederic (Box 2)
    - Mother's Day (Box 2)
    - Mountains (Box 2)
    - Nature (Box 2)
    - New Testament Characters (Box 2)
    - New Year (Box 2)
    - Occasional Addresses, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Old Testament Characters (Box 2)
    - Organ, The (Box 2)
    - Palm Sunday (Box 2)
    - Parables (Box 2)
    - Parables (Box 3)
      folders 2-3
    - Peace (Box 3)
    - I Peter (Box 3)
    - Philippians (Box 3)
    - Prayer, Meaning of (Box 3)
    - Prayers (Box 3)
    - Preparatory Sermons (Box 3)
    - Prohibition (Box 3)
    - Prophets (Box 3)
    - Rally Day (Box 3)
    - Revelation (Box 3)
    - Scripture Readings (Box 3)
    - Service, Meaning of (Box 3)
    - Smoking (Box 3)
    - Stewardship (Box 3)
    - Suffering (Box 3)
    - Thanksgiving (Box 3)
    - Theta Phi (Box 3)
    - Vacation, After (Box 3)
    - Washington, Church of The Covenant Call (Box 3)
    - Washington, George (Box 3)
    - Young People (Box 3)
  - Sermons, Addresses, Reviews, Memorials (by date)
    - Undated
      - A-F (includes untitled) (Box 3)
      - G-R (Box 3)
      - S-Z (Box 3)
    - 1918-1933, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - 1934-April 1943, 19 folders (Box 4)
    - May 1943-December 1951, 19 folders (Box 5)
    - January 1952-December 1958, 19 folders (Box 6)
    - 1959-1973, 16 folders (Box 7)
  - Thursday Noon Luncheon Club (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous (includes other family member materials) (Box 7)
  - Photographs (Box 7)
    Photographs of Willow Run, Michigan, housing, a local playground, and election campaigns.